Welcome to your lesson on the TikTok algorithm. In
this lesson, we're going to break down how the
algorithm works for each user, how you can apply
that knowledge as a creator who's trying to grow,
and the one major difference between TikTok and
Instagram's algorithms. As always, all
resources will be listed below. I stick to only
what TikTok themselves has said. I'll also link
general community guidelines to familiarize
yourself with because I'm not sure if you've
noticed, I will not be talking about shadow
banning in this video because most of the time when
I hear people or students say, oh, I think I'm
shadow banned, they're not. They just don't have
the right strategy. 99% of the time, we
accidentally self-sabotage our own growth by not
having the right strategy. And then we try to blame
it on an algorithm because that's easier than
taking responsibility. Yeah, I know that was a
little hard to hear, but don't worry, not you. With
this course, you will have the right strategies.
You will learn how to make high engaging videos and
you won't have to worry about being shadow banned.
So that's why we're not going to talk about it.
First things first, what is the algorithm? As you
may or may not know, there are hundreds and
thousands of algorithms operating at one time. to
help give a user the best experience across the
entire app, whether that's on the For You feed,
search, following, stem tab, live tabs, et
cetera. TikTok has stated that the foundation of
its algorithm is powered by a recommendation
system that delivers content to each user that is
likely to be of interest to that particular user.
In general, how this recommendation system works
is it'll suggest content to a user after taking
into account the user's preferences as expressed
through interactions in the app. Like if a user
watches a video, posts a comment, or follows an
account. This is why everybody's for you page or
FYP looks a little different to each other's. So
first let's break down the FYP recommendation
system. The For You feed is part of what enables
connection and discovery. Discovery being the
key word here, because this is where TikTok mostly
shows you content from accounts that you don't
already follow. They'll help you discover new
content, creators who are new to you, and new
creators. The simple way the algorithm works here
is really in two steps. Step one, TikTok studies
what a user is interested in. And then step two,
TikTok shows that user videos within their
interests that they will likely engage with. So
let's break that down a little bit. How does TikTok
study what each user is interested in? There are
three main ways. One, When someone creates a
TikTok account, they are asked what they're
interested in and what they're looking to
discover. This alone sets the parameters of what
their FYP will start to look like. The second way is
by looking at a user's device and account
settings, like your language preference,
country setting, location and time zone, your
device type or device settings. These factors are
only included to make sure the system is optimized
to your device's best performance and to
potentially show you content more relevant to you
based off of your generalized location and
country. This does not mean that you will only ever
see content that people post in your city because
TikTok has said that these factors, number two
factors, receive the lowest weight in their
recommendation system out of everything else.
Now, the third way that they study what each user is
interested in is by studying your interactions
and non-actions with the app, like posting a
comment or following an account. This one they
have said is probably the most important because
it is the most current data they have to analyze
every single day you open the app. Any sort of
action or inaction you make on the app is what
TikTok refers to as interest signals. Here are
just some of the interest signals that TikTok pays
attention to. Whether a user watches a video or
skips a video. If they did watch, how long did they
watch that video for? Are you liking, commenting,
saving, or sharing a piece of content? Which
accounts do you follow? Which accounts have you
followed more recently? and even the content you
create. Yes, the content you create affects what
you see in your For You page. This is why I recommend
having two accounts. One for strategically
growing your personal brand where you're posting
about certain things and therefore you're only
seeing certain things in your For You page. And
then another account for just mindlessly
scrolling for personal, for fun. We'll get into
that in another lesson. Now, once TikTok has an
idea of what a user is interested in, they will move
on to step two and then choose videos to put onto
your For You page. So let's break down how they
choose and identify those videos. Videos on the
For You page are ranked by looking at user's
interests and that video's information. So what
sort of information is important to the
algorithm? A video's captions, text, sounds,
hashtags, effects, trending topics, number of
views, and country or city it was posted or tagged
in. Then from there, TikTok tries its best to match
your interests with relevant videos that they
think you will engage with. So if I'm a user and I'm
scrolling and I skip past a bunch of makeup videos
but spend time watching and engaging with a lot of
dessert content, it's safe to assume I want more
desserts and recipes on my For You page. So TikTok
will then go out and find a variety of dessert
videos to start to show me. They will seek out
videos that have dessert mentioned in the caption
with the text on screen, showing a dessert in the
video, maybe even that hashtag. And because
they're trying to show me content they think I'll
engage with, they'll likely show me content or
videos that are relevant, but performing well. So
this could be videos with high engagement, high
views, or a long retention rate, things like that.
Same process applies if there's a sound that I
engage with a lot. It doesn't matter what the video
topic is, if I keep engaging with a sound, they will
continue to show me content with that sound. Or if I
recently made a search, again, my For You page will
start to show me videos relevant to that search.
They're analyzing every single move that I make to
try and keep my feed as relevant as possible to keep
me as a user scrolling for hours now before we talk
about how you can use this understanding of the
algorithm to your advantage as a creator because
that's why we're here let's quickly talk about
search because they will kind of overlap in a
second we see the tick tock search feature come up
in two main ways one search where you actually go to
search for content on tiktok and two in
recommended search terms throughout the app this
could be in search results under others searched
for or even on your for you page for you to discover
while scrolling you'll see a search term
recommended maybe under a video on your feed or in
the comments section of the video they will prompt
you to search for something. So that's where
search features are most relevant on the app. What
we're most interested in is understanding when
you search for something, how does TikTok choose
which videos to show up in results? The videos in
these results are sorted according to a
combination of factors. Here are some examples of
information that may influence the videos that
appear in search. relevance and content
information. Basically, how well does the
content match your search inquiry based on things
like video captions, video text, hashtags. Next
is engagement. how well a video is engaging with
its users. User interactions. TikTok also looks
at your past search behavior and the content you
like, share, comment on, or watch to determine
whose videos to pull up for you. If you recently
watched a video on clean eating on your For You page
and you saved it, and then a week later you search
for the term clean eating, that video might appear
or other videos from that specific creator might
appear. If you follow a specific creator, their
videos, if they're relevant to your search, might
appear in your search results or even another
creator similar to that person you follow. Then we
have user information. Again, this is like device
settings, language, preferences, and location.
Of these four factors, TikTok has said for most
users, content information, basically how well
the video content itself matches the specific
search entered. It's generally weighted more
heavily than any of the other factors. So with that
said, how can you use this knowledge to your
advantage when you start creating content?
Basically, what you need to do is become a
mastermind of who you want to reach. You need to
start thinking like the algorithm. Think about
your target audience. Think about what videos
they are engaging with what topics do they want to
see on their for you page what videos do they skip
and try to create the epitome of for you page
content for them that's why in the build section of
the courses in bsp i have you break down your target
audience so much because When you take the time to
understand who you want to reach, who you want to
impact, or even who you want to follow you, then you
can get even more specific and think about things
like, well, what are their goals right now? What
are they struggling with? How can I help them? How
can I create something that they can feel like they
relate to so they don't feel alone? What are they
searching for on TikTok? And then the answer to all
of those, how can I make a video that will help them
answer those questions? When you start to think
like an algorithm, you can literally predict what
sort of content will be most relevant to your
audience. Therefore, you basically get to
predict which videos will likely perform best for
you. Let's apply this practically. How can you
work with the algorithm to show up in search
results? First, think about your target
audience. What do you think they're searching for
on TikTok? Let's say your audience, they're
looking for low light houseplants. What you're
going to do is you're going to search that phrase on
TikTok. See what sort of videos are performing
well. What are the top videos? What vibe do they
have in common? With what you learn, you're going
to make a video talking about low light
houseplants. When you create that video, make
sure TikTok knows you're targeting that search.
Use the phrase, low light houseplants when
talking, in your caption, in the text on screen, in
the hashtags, anywhere you can. That is how you
work with the algorithm to hopefully show up in
search results. Now, how do you work with the
algorithm to show up on somebody's For You page?
Think about your audience, again, the same way the
algorithm would. The algorithm's number one
priority is studying what a user is interested in.
So ask yourself, type of content would my audience
want to see this one's harder because there's a
wider scope here for the for you page we know from
tick tock that this content could be on a specific
topic it could be a style of videos like get ready
with me's or story times or maybe there's a trend in
your niche or a trending audio that your audience
is engaging with so there's a little bit more
options here but you're going to pick one of those
aspects that you're pretty confident your
audience is interested in you're going to study
how others apply that aspect into their content to
create engaging videos, apply that to your own
content, and then post it with as much information
as possible so the algorithm knows your video is
relevant to that user. Again, utilizing
captions, text on the video, hashtags, sounds,
location tags, whatever it is that is relevant to
the video and to your audience. Now I know that
still kind of feels a little bit broad, but don't
worry because this lesson is just to explain the
algorithm, how it works, how you can generally
work with it. And as somebody who understands the
algorithm, I've already crafted all future
lessons to work with the algorithm for you. All you
have to do, if you just follow the steps in all
future lessons, you're already working with the
algorithm. To wrap this lesson up, I just wanna
mention the biggest difference between the
Instagram algorithm and the TikTok algorithm.
The reason being is I get a lot of people asking me
about the two, and also I see a lot of people either
coming from Instagram to grow on TikTok or
transfer from TikTok to growing on Instagram. As
we have learned today, TikTok's algorithm
studies each individual piece of content. So if
you post a video about running, they're gonna see
the topic, the general topic of that video, what
it's about. They're gonna try to push it to the
people who are interested in running. If you post a
video on houseplants, they're gonna try to find
the right audience for that video. So it doesn't
really matter what topic you post about because
TikTok will always try to get each individual
video to the right people. This is why on TikTok,
picking a niche is not as important because each
video has an equal chance equal opportunity to go
viral don't get me wrong picking a niche is still an
amazing strategy to grow faster grow quicker when
you're posting in one topic but their algorithm
allows you to be a little bit more flexible and have
a variety of interests and posts more what you want
instagram's algorithm first they create account
based embeddings this means they will try to
assign your profile to a specific topic this is why
on instagram you have to niche down you cannot post
about fashion and then makeup and then skin care
because those are too many topics when you're
posting about too many things Instagram will not
be able to create the proper account-based
embedding for you. They will not be able to
identify what topic you post about on the
platform. Each individual video doesn't really
get its own chance. They will get a good chance if
they're all under the same topic, but if you're
changing topics constantly, they don't know who
to push your content to and that's probably why you
won't see growth. As a reminder, all resources I
will link down below, including the TikTok
community guidelines. Be sure to familiarize
yourself with it. It's pretty simple to follow. So
long as you're following it, your account will be
in good standings. And I will see you in our next
lesson.